Register to the Poland, Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnętrznych issuances
Hoover Institution Archives
Poland, Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnętrznych issuances
1939-1946
(bulk, 1940-1945)
47020
Hoover Institution Archives
12 manuscript boxes (4.8 linear feet)
Reports and bulletins, relating to Polish politics and government; social conditions in Poland; the German and Soviet occupations of Poland; and the Polish underground movement during World War II. Includes reports and studies prepared by the Ministries of National Defense and Military Affairs.
Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnetrznych.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1947.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
As a direct result of the German and Soviet occupation of Poland, the government of the country was forced into exile in September 1939 with its first headquarters in Angers, France and later London, England. Polish government-in-exile, despite the situation in state, managed to hold considerable influence over what was happening in Poland at the time, largely due to the efforts of the Polish underground movement and the resilience of the Polish citizenry. Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnętrznych (MSW) (Ministry of Internal Affairs) did not form until 1940, while the government was in exile in London. The main role of MSW was to oversee the Polish underground state and to maintain a stable connection between the occupied country and the government-in-exile. While fulfilling its duties, the MSW received updates from the underground state on the social and physical condition of the occupied nations. As a result, the agency was able to produce various bulletins, communiques, reports and studies and thus chronicle the situation in 1940s occupied Poland.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection is composed of bulletins, communiques, and reports created by the Polish government-in-exile in London, particularly Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnętrznych, during the period of 1940-1945. The documents in the collection provide an overview of the Polish politics and government in-state during the period of German occupation. Materials discuss the social conditions in occupied Poland and provide detailed descriptions of terror, torture, false imprisonment, and extermination of Jews, Poles and various other nationalities residing in Poland during the time period. Additionally, the collection comprises of various studies focusing on the effect of war on children, concentration camps, educatin, and overviews of the situation on the western and eastern European lands under the control of German government.
Poland. Ministerstwo Obrony Narodowej.; Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Wojskowych.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; Poland--Social conditions.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.
- Bulletins and Communiques (Biuletyny I Komunikaty), 1940-1947
  Scope and Contents
  Documents comprised of various short news articles printed by Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnętrznych and Szefostwo Służby Opieki nad Żołnierzem. Created to keep the Poles residing abroad informed on the situation in Poland. Some of the topics reflected in the articles are education, religion, German military organization, Poland city traffic, supplies, military, state of ghettos in the country and more.
  - Informacje Ogólne, Nr. 13-30, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Informacje Ogólne, Nr. 31-47, 1946 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Informacje z Ziem Zachodnich, Nr. 1-12, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - La Decade Polonaise, Nr. 8, 1940 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Polish Fortnightly Review, Nr. 1-11, 1940 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Polish News Bulletin, Nr. 1, 78, 84, 1940 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Wiadomości Krajowe, Nr. 1/47 - 7/47, 1947 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Komunikaty Oświaty, Nr. 1/41 - 11/41, 1941 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Komunikaty Oświaty, Nr. 2/42 - 6/42, 1942 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Komunikaty Oświaty, Nr. 1/43 - 6/43, 1943 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Komunikaty Oświaty, Nr. 1/44 - 12/44, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Komunikaty Oświaty, Nr. 1/45 - 9/45, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Komunikaty Oświaty, Nr. 5/46 - 11/46, 1946 (Box-folder 2: 4)
- Reports (Sprawozdania), 1940-1945
  Files comprised of reports on a wide range of topics created by Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnętrznych. Topics reflected include but are not limited to: underground movement in Poland, agricultural situation in-state, communism, western and eastern lands of Europe, imprisonment, and concentration camps.
  - Sprawozdania, 1940 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Sprawozdania, 1941 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Sprawozdania, 1941 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. pierwszy/42, 1942 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 2/42, 1942 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 3/42, 1942 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 4/42, 1942 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 5/42, Część I, 1942 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 5/42, Część II, 1942 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 6/42, 1942 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 6/42, (English Translation), 1942 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 1/43, 1943 (Box-folder 4: 5-6)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 1/43 (English Translation), 1943 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 1-a/43, 1943 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 2/43, 1943 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 2-a/43, 1943 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 3/43, 1943 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 4/43, 1943 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 5/43, 1943 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 6/43, 1943 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 7/43, 1943 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 8/43, 1943 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 9/43, 1943 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 10/43, 1943 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 11/43, 1943 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 12/43, 1943 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 1/44, 1944 (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 1-a/44, 1944 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 2/44, 1944 (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 2-a/44, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 3/44, Część I i II, 1944 (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 4/44, 1944 (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 5/44, 1944 (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 6/44, 1944 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 7/44, 1944 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 8/44, 1944 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 9/44, 1944 (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 9-a/44, 1944 (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 10/44, 1944 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 11/44, 1944 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 12/44, 1944 (Box-folder 9: 2)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 13/44, 1944 (Box-folder 9: 3)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 13-a/44, 1944 (Box-folder 9: 4)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 14/44, 1944 (Box-folder 9: 5)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 15/44, 1944 (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 16/44, 1944 (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 16-a/44, 1944 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 17/44, 1944 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 18/44, 1944 (Box-folder 10: 2)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 18-a/44, 1944 (Box-folder 10: 3)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 1/45, 1945 (Box-folder 10: 4)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 2/45, 1945 (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 2-a/45, 1945 (Box-folder 10: 6)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 2-b/45, 1945 (Box-folder 10: 7)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 2-c/45, 1945 (Box-folder 10: 8)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 2-d/45, 1945 (Box-folder 10: 9)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 2-e/45, 1945 (Box-folder 10: 10)
  - Sprawozdanie, Nr. 3/45, 1945 (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - Sytuacja w Poslce - Raport, 1945 (Box-folder 11: 2)
- Studies (Opracowania), 1939-1945
  Studies focus on annexed territories, Soviet and German occupation, situation of children in occupied Poland, Polish museums, and public and private collections.
  - Agricultural Reconstruction, 1942 (Box-folder 11: 3)
  - Annexation, circa 1940 (Box-folder 11: 4)
  - Cele i Zadania Rady Zdrowia, 1941 (Box-folder 11: 5)
  - Children in an occupied state, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 11: 6)
  - Concentration Camps, circa 1942 (Box-folder 11: 7)
  - Działalność Władz Okupacyjnych, 1944 (Box-folder 11: 8)
  - Education, circa 1942 (Box-folder 11: 9)
  - Grupy Narodowościowe, circa 1940 (Box-folder 11: 10)
  - Museum, Private and Public Collections, 1944 (Box-folder 11: 11)
  - Occupation - German, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 11: 12)
  - Occupation - Soviet, circa 1944 (Box-folder 11: 13)
  - Overview of Studies by Mikołajczyk, circa 1942 (Box-folder 11: 14)
  - Polish National Liberation, 1945 (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - Prasa, circa 1940 (Box-folder 12: 2)
  - Provisional Estimate of Losses Sustained by Poland, 1944 (Box-folder 12: 3)
  - Terror, circa 1940 (Box-folder 12: 4)
  - Various Studies (assorted loose pages), 1939-1945 (Box-folder 12: 5)